Okay, בוקר טוב *boker tov*. Today's דף *daf* is עט *Ayin Tes*.
We pick up on the middle of עח עמוד ב *Ayin Ches
Amud Beis*, and we did the discussion in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
about ממזר mamzer *Mamzer*. It was a clear, pretty quick discussion considering
the importance of that subject. Don't worry, we're going to be seeing
more about that. Now we move on to the משנה Mishna. *Mishna*
that deals with the part of the משנה Mishna *Mishna* that deals
with the נתינים Nesinim, *Netinim*, that a נתין *Natin* is also forbidden.
And they are the גבעונים Givonim *Givonim*, and let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, which is one of the שבעה
עממים shiva amamim *Shiva Amamim*, seven Canaanite nations, that יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua*
made a pact with, because they had deceived him. And we are
going to take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Now, why
are they forbidden? Well, maybe it's the איסור issur *Issur* of לא
תתחתן בם lo sischaseim bam *Lo titchaten bam*. We saw a discussion
earlier whether that applies even after they've converted or not.
Let's take a look at
even after who, שבעת עממים *Shivat Amamim*?
After the גבעונים Givonim. *Givonim* converted. They are assumed to have converted
or else they would just be non-Jews. But now we're going to
see what else the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has to say about that.
So let's take a look.
Okay, אמר Amar, רבי Rabbi, חנא בר אדא *Amar Rabbi Chana bar
Adda*, the line starts with the word בר אדא *bar Adda*. Oh,
it's about 20 lines from the bottom. It's right after the... there's
a little bracket, square bracket with script on the right hand column,
and it's right across from that. So line starts with word בר
אדא *bar Adda*. אמר רבי Rabbi חנא בר אדא נתינים Nesinim דוד
David גזר עליהם gazar aleihem. *Amar Rabbi Chana bar Adda: Netinim David
gazar aleihem*. David, it was a... it was a rabbinic or whatever,
pre-rabbinic, at least post-biblical edict about the נתינים Netinim *Netinim*, presumably not
to intermarry with them. שנאמר She-ne'emar, *She'ne'emar*, and now we're going to
look at a passage in תנ"ך Tanakh *Tanakh* in שמואל *Shmuel* about
the גבעונים Givonim. *Givonim*, not the story with יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua*, but
a much later story.
ויקרא המלך לגבעונים Vayikra hamelech l'Givonim, ויאמר אליהם *Vayikra hamelech lagivonim vayomer
aleihem*. The king called the גבעונים Givonim *Givonim* and said to them,
והגבעונים לא מבני ישראל המה v'haGivonim lo mibnei Yisrael heimah, *Veha'givonim lo
mibnei Yisrael heim*, and they were not of the Jewish people. So
מאי טעמא גזר עליהם *Mai ta'ama gazar aleihem*, why did David make
an edict about intermarrying with them? דכתיב dichtiv *De'chtiv*, as the verse
says, ויהי רעב בימי דוד David שלוש שנים שנה אחרי שנה *Vayehi
ra'av bimei David shalosh shanim shana acharei shana*. There was a three
year famine in the time of David, three three consecutive years.
And then it says the פסוקים psukim *Pesukim* continue, that David David
asked God what it was about. And David said it was because
of the גבעונים Givonim, *Givonim* that were... that were decimated by שאול
Sha'ul *Shaul*. And as people know then the story continues that he
goes to the גבעונים Givonim *Givonim* and he says to them, what
can we do to appease you? And they say, give us the
sons of שאול Sha'ul *Shaul*, and they basically... and they... and they
hang them... and you know, the sons of שאול Sha'ul *Shaul* and
they remain hanging for a very long time. So let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says about this.
So year after year. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that there
was something happening each of those years, that David was trying to
get to the bottom of this right from the outset. שנה ראשונה
אמר להם *Shana rishona amar lahem*, the first year David said to
the people, שמא עובדי עבודה זרה יש בכם *Shema ovdei avodah zarah
yesh bachem*. Maybe there's idolaters among you and that's why we're having
this famine. דכתיב Di-ksiv, *De'chtiv*, the verse says, ועבדתם והשתחויתם להם ועצר
השמים ולא יהיה מטר *Ve'avadetem vehishtachaveitem lahem ve'atzar hashamayim velo yihyeh matar*.
That's one of the reasons why there's no rain. בדקו ולא מצאו
*Badku velo matzu*. So they investigated and they could not find that
there were any idolaters.
They only had a נביא *Navi*
that ever could have happened. All right. שניה אמר להם *Shniya amar
lahem*, the second year he said to them, שמא עוברי עבירה יש
בכם *Shema ovrei aveirah yesh bachem*. Maybe there are sinners, again עבירה
*Aveirah* here סתם stam *Stam* often means sexual sin. דכתיב Di-ksiv, *De'chtiv*,
וימנעו רביבים ומלקוש לא היה *Vayimane'u revivim umalkosh lo hayah*, that God
held back the rain and there was no rain, ומצח אשה זונה
היה לך *Umetzach isha zonah hayah lach*, and the forehead of a
brazen woman, of a prostitute woman, you had. So somehow that it's
a sin that results from sexual sin... it's a punishment that results
from sexual sin. בדקו ולא מצאו *Badku velo matzu*. They inspected and
they could not find. שלישית אמר להם *Shlishit amar lahem*, the third
year he said to them, שמא פוסקי צדקה ברבים יש בכם ואינם
נותנים *Shema porskei tzedakah b'rabim yesh bachem ve'einam notnim*. Maybe there are
among you those that make big... a pledge in when they're doing
an appeal and in in public and then they don't fulfill their
pledges. דכתיב *De'chtiv*, נשיאים ורוח וגשם אין In, *Nesi'im veruach vegeshem ayin*.
There is wind and clouds but no rain. And similarly, איש מתהלל
במתת שקר *Ish mithalel b'matat shaker*, a person who praises himself with
a false donation. So the same idea, there's all these signs that
there's going to be rain and then the rain never comes. You
know, like they have that phrase a rainmaker, right, somebody who brings
in the money. Okay, anyway, so maybe that's why there's no rain.
בדקו ולא מצאו *Badku velo matzu*. Anyway, so they checked and they
could not find. אמר *Amar*, so, okay, אין הדבר תלוי אלא בי
ein hadavar talui ela bi *Ein hadavar taluy ela bi*. It's up
to me to figure out what's about, which is pretty funny because
it was... what do you mean it's my fault? Yeah, well, I
don't even know if he means it's my fault, but let's take
a look. מיד mi-yad, ויבקש דוד David את פני השם *Miyad vayevakesh
David et pnei Hashem*. David asked God, which is pretty funny, I
don't get the exact transition of אין הדבר תלוי אלא בי ein
hadavar talui ela bi *Ein hadavar taluy ela bi*. He's been trying
to figure it out for the last three years. So now the
fact that he's turning straight to God rather than turning to the
people? Anyway, so David turned to God. מאי היא *Mai hi*, so
what does that mean? How did he turn to God? אמר ריש
לקיש ששאל באורים ותומים *Amar Resh Lakish she'sha'al ba'urim vetummim*. Right, he
asked the Urim and Thummim. מאי משמע *Mai mashma*, how do you
know that means to ask directly God? אמר רבי Rebbi אלעזר אתיא
פני פני *Amar Rabbi Elazar atya pnei pnei*. We make a גזירה
gezeirah שוה *Gezerah shavah* from the word "the face of". כתיב הכא
ויבקש דוד David, את פני השם *Ktiv hacha vayevakesh David et pnei
Hashem*, וכתיב התם ושאלו לו במשפט האורים לפני lifnei. השם *U'chtiv hatam
vesha'alu lo b'mishpat ha'urim lifnei Hashem*. Okay, in front of God, פני
*pnei*. פני, לפני. All right, anyway. ויאמר השם שאול ואל בית הדמים.
Vayomer Hashem sha'ul v'el beit hadamim. So God answered דוד Dovid and
said, it is because of שאול Sha'ul and because of the house
of blood, על אשר המית הגבעונים, al asher hemit hagivonim, because he
killed the Gibeonites. So what does this mean other than the פשט?
pshat? על שאול שלא נספד כהלכה. Al Sha'ul shelo nispas ke'halacha. שאול
Sha'ul was not mourned appropriately. Now where are they getting that from?
They're getting that from because, well yes I know, but what's motivating
them to interpret it that way since it seems clearly it's about
the Gibeonites? Because if you read the story in תנ"ך at the
end of the story and after all the episode with the Gibeonites
and with the sons of שאול Sha'ul being hanged and all of
that, it says at the very end that דוד Dovid went and
he retrieved the bones of שאול Sha'ul and the bones of יהונתן
Yehonatan that had been captured in the battle with the פלשתים Plishtim
and he basically reburied them. And he also reburied the bones of
the bodies of his sons that were, we're going to see, were
executed. So at the end of the whole story, although it's all
talking about the Gibeonites, the end of the story talks about דוד
Dovid reburying שאול Sha'ul and יהונתן. Yehonatan. So therefore the גמרא Gemara
sees that that was part of what was said at the very
outset, that he is being punished because שאול Sha'ul never received a
proper burial or a proper הספד hesped at his death. על שאול
שלא נספד כהלכה, Al Sha'ul shelo nispas ke'halacha, ועל בית הדמים על
אשר המית הגבעונים, v'el beit hadamim al asher hemit hagivonim,
and because שאול Sha'ul sort of slaughtered the Gibeonites. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, וכי היכן מצינו בשאול שהמית את הגבעונים, v'chi heichan
matzinu b'sha'ul shehemit et hagivonim,
where do we ever find that happened prior? Because it doesn't say
it anywhere prior in the narrative. Here it says that שאול Sha'ul
did it and here it actually says that he tried, that he
tried to decimate them. So okay, but you know the גמרא Gemara
wants to know like where's there ever any evidence that he did
it before? אלא מתוך שהרג נוב עיר כהנים, Ela mitoch sheharag Nov
ir Kohanim, but when he wiped out נוב, Nov, the city of
כהנים, Kohanim, when he was running after trying to kill דוד, Dovid
שהיו מספיקין להם מים ומזון, shehayu maspikin lahem mayim u'mazon, and the
Gibeonites worked for the כהנים, Kohanim, they were the hewers of water
and the drawers of water and they worked for the priests. So
therefore, we're assuming that that's what they did. I mean the גמרא
Gemara, is going to assume it later on. I don't know because
it said but because by
יהושע Yehoshua it says that he gave them over to hewers of
water למזבח השם, l'mizbe'ach Hashem, for the altar of God. Okay, so
therefore since they are assumed to have been working for the priests,
once all the priests are wiped out, so therefore they're not getting
their sustenance either, no paycheck. מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו הרגם. Ma'aleh alav
hakatuv k'ilu haragam.
It's like they killed them, right? So you know, what's that joke
from the חפץ חיים? Chofetz Chaim? Because you had a bad day,
why should I suffer? So here you go, the נוב, Nov, the
whole city was wiped out, נעבעך, nebech, so now the גבעונים Givonim
aren't getting their paycheck. So that's obviously taking something which in the
פסוקים psukim is much more drastic and the פסוקים psukim? it sounds
like שאול Sha'ul really tried to wipe them all out and here
it's saying that it was just because well he wiped other people
out, he wiped out the כהנים, Kohanim, but that indirectly affected them,
yes?
Okay, just want to take a step back. So the Gibeonites were
the exception that they were from the שבעה עממים shiva amamim, that
like you know deceived their way in. By a regular שבעה עממים,
shiva amamim, you can't accept them as converts, right? Whether or not
you have to
do deep down,
that's not how it works.
Yeah, so I'm not, so that's too complex. I'm not getting into
that, but it's so clear that the איסור issur of,
that's the question, is the מצוה mitzvah to wipe out the שבעה
עממים, shiv'ah amemim does it apply even after they've converted? That's actually
a debate. But the point here is that whether also the prohibition
of marrying applies as well. But let's keep on going, okay? That's,
I mean it'll take more time to answer that. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says, קתני על שאול שלא נספד כהלכה וקתני
על אשר המית הגבעונים. Katani al sha'ul shelo nispas ke'halacha v'katani al
asher hemit hagivonim. I don't get it. Like is שאול Sha'ul here
a good guy or a bad guy? First you're defending שאול's Sha'ul
honor that he was not eulogized properly and then you're taking him
to task because he wiped out the Gibeonites. Does that make sense
that you know you're being punished for these two things? I mean
you know one for not treating שאול Sha'ul properly and the other
for שאול Sha'ul having done this terrible thing? אין, yeah. דאמר ריש
לקיש, D'amar Resh Lakish, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the
verse, בקשו את השם כל ענוי הארץ,
bikshu et Hashem kol
anvei ha'aretz,
seek out God all the you know the humble of the land,
אשר משפטו פעלו, asher mishpato pa'alu,
that God's justice they have done. אשר משפטו שם פעלו, Asher mishpato
sham pa'alu,
where God's justice is, that's where God's deeds are. Meaning at the
same place that God exacts justice, God also shows you know that
God's righteousness and God's you know and God's acting in to show
proper you know to to give people their due. So the same
way it's also where שאול Sha'ul, is being judged, but it's also
where שאול Shaul is being given his due. אמר דוד, Amar David,
שאול נפלו ליה תריסר ירחי שתא. Sha'ul naflu leh t'risar yarchei shata.
So I'm here being called to task or the people are being
punished for these two things. שאול Shaul, not being eulogized and the
Gibeonites.
Well, eulogizing שאול, it's a little late. It's been more than already
twelve months. It's not exactly the high highest priority or the best
time to do. I mean twelve twelve months, excuse me. But as
תוספות Tosafot points out or רש"י Rashi points out, it's actually been
thirty years. Okay, but it's also been twelve months. Once the year
is over to all of a sudden do a הספד. hesped. See,
that's not the most immediately pressing thing, it's not the best time.
Again, as I said, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't quote it, at
the end of this narrative it speaks about them reburying the bones
of שאול in a proper burial place, but דוד Dovid. was saying
that's not the highest priority. ולא דחא למספדי, Velo dacha l'mispedei, it's
not appropriate to eulogize it at this late time. נתינים, Nesinim, so
let's worry about the גבעונים. Givonim נקרינהו ונפייסינהו, Nikrina u'nepaysinu,
let's call them and appease them. ויקרא המלך לגבעונים, so the king
called the גבעונים. Givonim ויאמר להם, Vayomer lahem, and he said to
them, מה אעשה לכם, Mah e'eseh lachem, what will I do for
you, ובמה אכפר, U'bamah achaper, and how may it be atoned, וברכו
את נחלת השם, U'varchu es nachalas Hashem, and you will bless the
inheritance of God. ויאמרו לו הגבעונים, Vayomru lo haGivonim, the גבעונים Givonim,
said to him, אין לנו כסף וזהב עם שאול, Ein lanu kesef
v'zahav im Shaul, we don't want any money and we don't have
any claim against him for gold and silver, ועם ביתו, V'im beiso,
or against his house, ואין לנו איש מישראל, v'ein lanu ish m'Yisrael,
so and we don't want any man from amongst the general people.
All we want is not money, not silver, not gold, no person
from among the general people, all we want are seven of his
sons. ינתן לנו שבעה אנשים מבניו, Yutan lanu shiv'ah anashim mibanav, give
us seven of his sons, והוקענום להשם, v'hokanum l'Hashem, and we will
sort of, you know, impale them before God against the sun, you
know, and that will be shown that we'll be, that justice will
have been done against his household. So מפייס לא פייסינהו, Mifas lo
faysinu, so he tried to appease them some other way and they
weren't having anything of it. אמר, he said, so דוד Dovid now
felt like, you know, this tremendous cruelty that he was seeing from
these people. So he said, שלשה סימנים יש באומה זו, Shloshah simanim
yesh b'umah zu, the Jewish people, not the גבעונים, the Jewish people
have three identifying characteristics: הרחמנים, Harachmanim, they are compassionate, והביישנים, v'habayshanim, and
they are, you know, shameful, they're able to be embarrassed, וגומלי חסדים,
v'gomlei chasadim,
and they do acts of kindness. רחמנים דכתיב Rachmanim dichtiv ונתן לך
רחמים ורחמך והרבך, v'nasan lecha rachamim v'richamcha v'hirbecha, God will give you
compassion and you will have compassion. ביישנים דכתיב Bayshanim dichtiv
that they are embarrassed and ashamed when they do something wrong, you
know, and they're not brazen, דכתיב בעבור תהיה יראתו על פניכם לבלתי
תחטאו, ba'avur tihyeh yir'aso al pneichem l'vilti sechetau,
God is giving you the Torah directly so that you shall have
fear of God and not sin, so that you act in a
humble way and a non-brazen way. And וגומלי חסדים דכתיב v'gomlei chasadim
dichtiv למען אשר יצוה את בניו ואת ביתו אחריו ושמרו דרך השם
לעשות צדקה ומשפט, l'ma'an asher yetzaveh es banav v'es beiso acharav v'shamru
derech Hashem la'asos tzedakah u'mishpat, and to do the way of God
to do righteousness and justice. כל שיש בו שלשה סימנים הללו, Kol
sheyesh bo shloshah simanim elalu, if anybody has, any other nation has
these three characteristics, ראוי להדבק באומה זו, ra'uy l'hidabek b'umah zu,
that would be appropriate to intermarry, I mean assuming they converted. But
if you don't have these three characteristics, so here the גבעונים are
acting in such this cruel and heartless way, clearly it is never
appropriate for us to intermarry. So this is what the גמרא Gemara
is getting at where we see דוד Dovid וגזר עליהם. v'gazar aleihem.
Okay, because of this cruel way they act, we can speculate or
we can assume that דוד Dovid said if that's how they're acting,
we should never marry in them even if they've converted and even
if technically they're Jewish, but because of their national characteristics we should
never intermarry with them. Some want to hinge it on the fact
that the פסוק pasuk says when it introduces the גבעונים in the
story, והגבעונים לא מבני ישראל המה, lo mibnei Yisrael heimah
which לא מבני ישראל mibnei Yisrael המה means not just they weren't
originally מבני ישראל but they were never going to be part of
בני ישראל bnei Yisrael in the sense of never marry among them
and to see that with a גזירה gezeirah of דוד. Dovid Now,
I do want to stop here for a moment and say that
תוספות Tosafos has three explanations what the גזירה gezeirah of דוד Dovid
was. One because the question is, look, if they were from the
שבעה עממים shiv'ah amemim weren't they already אסור? assur? So there was
a debate before whether the Torah what it says לא תתחתן בם
lo sischaseim bam by the שבעה עממים shiv'ah amemim apply even after
they've converted or not. So one explanation is that it only applies
when they were non-Jews. After they've converted it does not apply. And
therefore that's why you needed this גזירה gezeirah by דוד Dovid to
say that even though they've converted, you can't intermarry them. Even there
תוספות Tosafos has two explanations because we're going to see later the
גמרא Gemara is going to deal with the fact that by יהושע
Yehoshua he made them into like slaves or servants or so on.
So one explanation that תוספות Tosafos is going to have is that,
you know, יהושע Yehoshua maybe made them into slaves, but they weren't
really slaves, they were servants, not slaves, or whatever they were anyway.
And דוד Dovid made it forbidden to marry them. A second explanation
he gives is that דוד Dovid actually reaffirmed יהושע's—I'm Yehoshua jumping a
little ahead, we'll see about this—but anyway somehow
reaffirmed יהושע's Yehoshua גזירה gezeirah that they would be treated as servants/slaves.
And naturally as a result of their status as slaves, it's אסור
assur to marry them because it's אסור assur to marry slaves. So
it was like indirect. I don't think that's so much פשט. pshat.
I think the פשט pshat more is that he directly said it
was אסור assur to marry them. But the third answer תוספות Tosafos
gives is—this discusses is—let's say they're דאורייתא d'Oraisa forbidden to marry, right?
So if they're דאורייתא d'Oraisa forbidden to marry that לא תתחתן בם
applies even by the שבעה עממים after they've converted, then what did
דוד Dovid do? And according to that, דוד David didn't make any
גזירה Gezeirah not to marry them, because דוד's David was only basically
to basically continue to treat them as
servants/slaves. Okay? So there were what? Yeah, well we'll see later, but
like maybe it wouldn't have applied when there wasn't a בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and in the time of דוד David there wasn't... בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So anyway, I just want to point out
that the simple sense of the גמרא, Gemara, I would say, because
right here, it's talking about marrying them. There's no hint here that
we're talking about slaves. The whole discussion of this מסכת masechet is
about who can you marry or not marry. So later we'll be
introduced to the issue about the נתינים Nesinim and their status from
the time of יהושע Yehoshua. as slaves, but right now that seems
completely irrelevant and certainly the פשט pshat here is as that it's
not a biblically problematic, maybe because they converted, but דוד David said,
you know, this is not a people we want to intermarry with
even if they've converted because of these characteristics and therefore he was
גזר עליהם.
Yes. אין הדבר תלוי אלא ela בי bi? seems to be that
first thing he looked for fault among the people, right? It's much
easier to see faults in other people than do something that was
his responsibility. That's what I understand.
Oh, it seems responsible for the בי? But why was it his
responsibility? You mean because since it was something
that only he could implement the
correction I guess.
Uh-huh, yeah, but until he sort of realized what the problem was,
right? You know what I'm saying, like אין הדבר תלוי אלא בי
only makes sense after he realized what the problem
was. It was still at a stage where he didn't know. No,
he sort of said, okay, it wasn't some sin the people did.
I mean, unless you're saying it must be something that was my
responsibility and the only way I can find out what I haven't
done that's my responsibility is by asking God. But he had some
sense that it was something that was uniquely his responsibility. Okay, maybe.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, let's take a look.
Okay, so that's why he נתגזר עליהם. nitgazar aleihem. Now he continue
in the story. Okay, ויקח המלך את שני בני רצפה בת איה
אשר ילדה לשאול.
Vayikach hamelech es shenei benei Ritzpah
bas Ayah asher yaldah le'Shaul.
So he gave them over seven sons. Which seven? The two sons
of רצפה Ritzpah the daughter of איה Ayah who was children of
שאול, את
ארמוני ואת מפיבשת. es Armoni ve'es Mephiboshes. This was not the מפיבשת
Mephiboshes that was יהונתן Yehonasan's son because the פסוק posuk says right
before that he had compassion on מפיבשת יהונתן Mephiboshes Yehonasan's son because
of the promise that he gave to יהונתן. Yehonasan. So there were
two מפיבשת. Mephiboshes. ואת חמשת בני מיכל בת שאול Ve'es chameshes benei
Michal bas Shaul the five daughters
of מיכל Michal אשר ילדה לעדריאל בן ברזילי המחולתי asher yaldah le'Adriel
ben Barzillai ha-Mecholasi that he gave birth to עדריאל בן ברזילי המחולתי.
Adriel ben Barzillai ha-Mecholasi. Now מיכל Michal was also his wife, right?
So this was kids of his wife from another marriage. Oh, so
funny. Anyway, okay, fine. Same Michal that was so cynical
after she said those things like... Yeah, had they been married before?
Yeah, apparently, I don't know. Anyway, she had kids later.
Yeah, right, well, yeah, but okay. מאי שנא הני? Mai shena hani?
So why specifically these seven? How did he pick which seven? אמר
רב הונא העבירום לפני הארון. Amar Rav Huna ha'aviroom lifnei ha-aron. This
as you might remember this is a similar story we had before
about how did משה Moshe know at the time of פנחס Pinchas
and the מדינים Midyanim which women had had sex or not. Anyway,
he made them pass before the ארון. aron. כל שהארון קולטו, Kol
sheha-aron kolto, anyone that was sort of absorbed by the ארון, aron,
not exactly sure what that means, but know, pulled in, למיתה, lemisah,
would get put to death. Which is funny because normally the ארון
aron is an idea of like the מזבח, mizbe'ach, right, this idea
of sanctuary, right? מעם מזבחי תקחנו למות, Me-im mizbechi tikachenu lamus, yet
the fact that you're being pulled in shows that you're for death.
למיתה. Lemisah. כל שאין הארון קולטו, Kol she'ein ha-aron kolto, לחיים. lechayim.
I don't know why it said ארון aron and not the אורים
ותומים. Urim Ve-Tumim. Anyway, מתיב רב חנא בר קטינא, Masiv Rav Chana
bar Katina, ויחמול המלך על מפיבשת בן יהונתן בן שאול. Vayachmol hamelech
al Mephiboshes ben Yehonasan ben Shaul. It
said that the king had compassion on מפיבשת, Mephiboshes, which sounds like
if it was all determined by the ארון, aron, what good is
his compassion, right? It sounds like it was totally his discretion. So
how what good is his compassion? It was a different מפיבשת. Mephiboshes.
שלא העבירו. Shelo he'eviro. No, the compassion was he didn't have to
do the test. Okay, so he exempted מפיבשת Mephiboshes from the test.
That was the compassion. וכי משוא פנים יש בדבר? Vechi maso panim
yesh badavar?
What, can you show favoritism? And רש"י Rashi so I mean how
well, okay, it's not fair, let God decide. אלא שהעבירו וקלטו. Ela
shehe'eviro vekalto. All
right, so he did pass מפיבשת Mephiboshes and מפיבשת Mephiboshes was taken
in by the ארון. aron. וביקש עליו רחמים ופלטו. Uvikes alav rachamim
upalto. But then he prayed and then the ארון aron spit him
back out. ואכתי משוא פנים יש בדבר? Ve-achti maso panim yesh badavar?
Still, you know, is there favoritism? Is that fair? Now there's a
very powerful רש"י Rashi which reminds you of some stories from the
Holocaust. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, וכי משוא פנים יש בדבר
vechi maso panim yesh badavar about I don't know, 12 lines down
in the narrow lines. רש"י Rashi says, וכי היה לו לדוד לישא
פנים בדיני נפשות, vechi hayah lo le-Dovid lisa panim be-dinei nefashos, היה
לו להעביר את כולם, hayah lo le-ha'avir es kulam, ואכתי משוא פנים
יש בדבר הואיל וקלטו ארון לא היה לו להמית
אחר תחתיו. ve-achti maso panim yesh badavar ho'il vekalto aron lo hayah
lo le-hamis acher tachtav.
Right, so by praying for compassion for him, you're basically assigning somebody
else to death in his place, right? And those were, you know,
some of those really like impossible, you know, scenarios in the Holocaust
where you wanted to save one person, saving one person means putting
somebody else on the, you know, on the train instead.
But the point of this explanation is not so bad, meaning they
only
want to seven people, you put seven people before, you got exactly...
Right, I understand the משוא פנים maso panim in the first case
is less bad, but then once he's chosen and then basically essentially
freeing him which is putting somebody else in his place, אלא so
the גמרא Gemara corrects, אלא שביקש רחמים שלא יקלטנו ארון. ela shebikes
rachamim shelo yikletenu aron.
He prayed initially that he would never be accepted. So he went
through the test, but he was he was trying to appease God
that he should not be. Somehow that makes sense. Okay והכתיב לא
יומתו אבות על בנים. V'haktiv lo yumtu avot al banim. Fine so
these seven sons were given over but how was that appropriate? It
says that the children will not have to pay die for the
father's sins and here that's exactly what's happening. So אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan מוטב שתעקר אות אחת מן התורה mutav she-te'aker ot achat min
ha-Torah better one letter from the תורה Torah should be uprooted—seems like
more than one letter—ואל יתחלל שם שמים בפרהסיא v'al yitchalel Shem Shamayim
b'farhesya should not be a public desecration of the divine name. Now
that's pretty interesting, you would think maybe
slaughtering innocent people
is a public desecration of the divine name. Why would it be
a public desecration of the divine name if you wouldn't do it?
So if you look at רשי, Rashi, רשי Rashi says, he says
יתחלל שם שמים yitchalel Shem Shamayim יתחלל שם שמים yitchalel Shem Shamayim
שיהו האומות אומרים אין אומה זו ראויה לידבק בה she-yehu ha-umot omrim
ein uma zo re-uyah l'hidabek bah this is not a proper nation
that fits to cleave to it שהרי פשטו ידיהם בגרים she-harei pashtu
yadeihem b'gerim ליטול מזונותיהם litol mezonoteihem and again remember the גמרא Gemara
is framing it that all they did wrong was that they were
no longer being provided for, not that they were literally
killed. So here was these converts that they're no longer providing for
their food ועשו בהם נקמה v'asu bahem nekamah and vengeance wasn't done
for them. So because people will perceive this as a terrible thing,
therefore it was better that you give over these seven, that you
violate this law of the תורה Torah and give over these seven
sons to be killed, which is pretty radical if you think about
it especially because there's often a question is חילול השם Chilul Hashem
in the eyes of Jews is it in the eyes of non-Jews.
Here clearly it's in the eyes of non-Jews. You could say that
their standards are totally
pervert, that they would think that this is
a perverse sense of justice. And nevertheless, the fact that
we're concerned about perception even if we might think it's perverse and
even if it goes against our sense of justice because of the
sense of חילול השם Chilul Hashem even to the point that we're
allowing people to be killed. So it's pretty radical when you think
about the issue about a concern about how we present ourselves to
the outside world. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
continues, so that's how they allowed it to happen
מן התורה min ha-Torah that they were uprooting was והכתיב לא יומתו
אבות על בנים. V'haktiv lo yumtu avot al banim. Exactly, exactly.
Now ותקח רצפה בת איה את השק Vatikkach Ritzpah bat Ayah et
hasak so רצפה Ritzpah the daughter of איה Ayah who was one
of the mothers of two of them took the sackcloth ותטהו לה
אל הצור vatatehu lah el hatzur and she stretched it out by
the rock מתחלת קציר עד נתך מים עליהם מן השמים mitchillat katzir
ad nitach mayim aleihem min hashamayim from the beginning of the harvest
season until rain fell upon them from the heavens. ולא נתנה עוף
השמים לנוח עליהם יומם וחית השדה לילה v'lo natnah of hashamayim lanoach
aleihem yomam v'chayat hasadeh laylah she did not let the birds of
the heaven rest on them, the
bodies, by day, or the beast to the field to attack them
at
night. And they stood there impaled and hung for many months until
finally it rained. והכתיב לא תלין נבלתו על העץ V'haktiv lo talin
nivlato al ha-etz does the verse not say, 'You shall not let
the carcass
stay
on the wood', אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan even for one
night?
אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק mishum
Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak מוטב שתעקר אות אחת מן התורה ויתקדש שם
שמים בפרהסיא mutav she-te'aker ot achat min ha-Torah v'yitkadesh Shem Shamayim b'farhesya
same story, we'll allow this idea of not leaving the bodies unburied
to be violated in order to cause a קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem,
not just not a חילול השם Chilul Hashem but a קידוש השם.
Kiddush Hashem. What's the קידוש השם? Kiddush Hashem? שהיו עוברים ושבים אומרים
she-hayu ovrim v'shavim omrim because now bystanders will say, passers-by will say
מה טיבן של אלו mah tivan shel elu why are these people,
these bodies being hung here? What's going on
here? הללו בני מלכים הם hallalu b'nei melachim hem oh, these are
the sons of
kings, these are princes. ומה עשו u'mah asu and what did they
do that they deserve this punishment? פשטו ידיהם בגרים גרורים pashtu yadeihem
b'gerim grurim they acted against
lowly converts. It's גרים, gerim, they weren't their גר, ger, like schlepping
along גרים. gerim. Why? Because they converted under deception, they weren't like
the most sincere converts. These were even sort of deceptive converts. And
nevertheless, this was what their punishment was even though the people were
what normally would have been considered second or third-class citizens. אמרו אין
לך אומה שראויה לידבק בה כזו amru ein l'cha uma she-re-uyah l'hidabek
bah k'zo there's no nation that's fit to cleave to as this.
ומה בני מלכים כך u'mah b'nei melachim kach and if that's how
they'll punish princes for this act that they've done against these sort
of
people that weren't even a primary part of the nation בני הדיוטות
על אחת כמה וכמה b'nei hedyotot al achat kamah v'chamah how much
more so will they be demanding of even common people and of
what high ethical standards they have. So it's quite fascinating, it sort
of
flipped it. Here Saul did this terrible thing, but in the end
it's the גבעונים that are acting heartless and we become the people
that are demonstrated to have these tremendous high ethical standards. And again
notice this idea of קידוש שם שמים Kiddush Shem Shamayim because of
all based on this larger
perception. Also notice the echoing of ראוי לידבק באומה זו. ra-uy l'hidabek
b'uma zo. David sees how the נתינים Nesinim. are asking and he's
saying they're not fit to be part of our nation. Everybody else
sees what our standards are and you could say our standards are
also cruel, we allowed these seven people to be killed, but that's
not seen as cruel. For us, that is seen as קידוש שם
שמיים, Kiddush Shem Shamayim, we're giving in to the גבעונים and that
makes everybody want to marry with us.
Okay, so how far can you extend this
principle?
That I don't know, that's why I'm mentioning it. I don't know
the answer to that. By the way, תוספות Tosfos quotes a nice
מדרש, Midrash, ותטה
אל הצור. Va-tateil el ha-tzur. So תוספות Tosfos says, אומר במדרש, omer
ba-Midrash, אל הצור, el ha-tzur, שהצדיקה עליה הדין ואמרה הצור תמים פעלו,
she-hitzdika aleha hadin ve-amra HaTzur Tamim Pe'alo, a play on the word
הצור, HaTzur, right? So the צידוק הדין tzidduk hadin is הצור תמים
פעלו, HaTzur Tamim Pe'alo, so he's saying that's what she, the mother,
must have said, you know, at this time when this was happening
to her sons. Okay, so מיד, immediately as a result of this
that everybody realized how amazing the Jewish people were and their high
ethical standards, נתווספו ישראל מאה וחמישים אלף, nisvasfu Yisrael me'ah ve-chamishim elef,
150,000 people converted to the Jewish people, שנאמר, She-ne'emar, as it says,
ויהי לשלמה שבעים אלף נושא סבל, Vayihi li-Shelomo shiv'im elef nosei sabal,
so the 70,000 people that would carry like the burdens, ושמונים אלף
חוצב בהר, u-shmonim elef chotzeiv ba-har,
and 80,000 hewers in the mountain. This is to build the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Of course, goes against the other idea that they
didn't accept converts in the time of דוד David, and שלמה. Shlomo.
What do you, what should I say? שנאמר, shene'emar ודילמא ישראל
הוו, ve-dilma Yisrael havu,
maybe it means they had 150,000 people that were not converted, but
that somehow were hangers-on of the nation. Anyway, maybe they were, okay,
anyway, maybe they were naturally born Jews, maybe they weren't from the
outside nations. הוו להו, לא סלקא דעתך, Havu lehu, lo salika daiteich,
that doesn't make sense. דכתיב, ומבני ישראל לא נתן שלמה עבד, Di-ksiv,
u-mibnei Yisrael lo nasan Shlomo eved, שלמה Shlomo did not make בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael into, he did not give them servitude, and here
this sounds like a type of a servitude, so clearly they're
from the gentiles. So the גמרא Gemara, says, ודילמא דוכסא בעלמא, ve-dilma
dugsar be-alma, which is some type of a loanword, but anyway, who
says that this means that they gave servitude? Maybe this was a
daily, you know, they were day laborers. So again, how do you
know these weren't Jews? How do you know these were from the
other nations? אמר הכא, Omei hacha, from the following verse, ויספור שלמה
כל האנשים הגרים אשר בארץ ישראל. Vayispor Shlomo kol ha-anashim ha-geirim asher
be-eretz Yisrael. תוספות, Tosfos, and שלמה Shlomo recorded all of the people
that were dwelling in Israel, וימצאו מאה וחמישים אלף, vayimatze'u me'ah ve-chamishim
elef, 150,000, וישם מהם שבעים אלף סבל, Vayasem mehem shiv'im elef sabal,
70,000
again bearers of burden, ושמונים אלף חוצב בהר, u-shmonim elef chotzeiv ba-har,
and 80,000 hewers in the mountain. So anyway, since it says הגרים
אשר בישראל ha-geirim asher be-Yisrael
that were dwelling in Israel, he understands it means that they were
not themselves Israel. Although I looked up the פסוק pasuk last night
and it doesn't have that phrase הגרים אשר בישראל. ha-geirim asher be-Yisrael.
Does somebody here have the the whole quote of the פסוקים? psukim,
Unless I was looking at the wrong פסוקים, but in דברי הימים
ב' ב' Divrei HaYamim Beis Beis it did not say הגרים אשר
בישראל. ha-geirim asher be-Yisrael. It just said ויספור שלמה vayispor Shlomo and
then it said וימצאו מאה וחמישים אלף. vayimatze'u me'ah ve-chamishim elef.
Anyway, Charlie is going to check it out. Okay, anyway, moving on.
All right. So 150,000 people came on.
ויספור שלמה כל האנשים הגרים אשר,
Vayispor
Shlomo
kol ha-anashim ha-geirim asher,
oh,
how did I miss it? Where is that?
It's after verse 16.
Oh, I was looking at 2:2:1. So it must have been again,
okay, fine. So a similar פסוק pasuk was at 2:2:1, but here
it repeats it, it says הגרים אשר בישראל. ha-geirim asher be-Yisrael. Okay,
fine. Moving on. אשר בארץ Asher be-eretz whatever. Okay, moving on. Okay,
ונתינים דוד גזר עליהם. ve-Nesinim David gazar aleihem. So that's why דוד
David did, because that whole story, it was not fit to marry
them. ונתינים דוד גזר עליהם, ve-Nesinim David gazar aleihem, did דוד David,
make the edict? משה גזר עליהם, Moshe gazar aleihem, משה Moshe did.
And here we're going to see this sort of intertwining of the
idea of not marrying with the idea of servitude.
דכתיב, it says מחטב עציך עד
שואב מימיך, mi-chotev eitzcha ad sho'ev meimecha, from those that are the
hewers of stone to the drawers of water. And we know by
יהושע Yehoshua they were made hewers of, hewers of wood. So therefore
somehow it's assuming that even by the time of משה, Moshe, he
had identified a people to be hewers of wood. Exactly how it
works, they weren't yet in ארץ כנען, Eretz Kna'an, and they didn't
yet have them making the pact. I don't know exactly, but somehow
we're assuming that משה Moshe had already identified a people as hewers
of wood. And because of that you couldn't marry them? Well, so
that's a question. Does it mean that משה Moshe just made them
slaves and are we dealing with a different subject? Or if they're
slaves, then you're not allowed to marry a slave. So the גמרא,
Gemara so that's why these things get intertwined. So the גמרא Gemara,
says משה גזר להו דרא, Moshe gazar le-hu dara, משה Moshe only
made for that generation. דוד גזר לכולי דרא, David gazar le-chulei dara,
דוד David made for future generations. ואיכא יהושע גזר עלי, Ve-aka Yehoshua
gazar alai, but it was not דוד, David it was יהושע. Yehoshua,
דכתיב, and here's really where we first encounter the גבעונים, ויתנם יהושע
ביום ההוא חוטבי עצים ושואבי מים לעדה ולמזבח ה', Vayisnem Yehoshua ba-yom
ha-hu chotevei eitzim ve-sho'avei mayim la-eidah u-le-mizbeach Hashem, he made them hewers
of wood and drawers of water for the nation and for the
altar. That's here we get the connection to the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. יהושע גזר בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, Yehoshua gazar bi-zman she-Beis HaMikdash
kayam, because it says למזבח ה', li-mizbeach Hashem, יהושע said when there
is a temple. Of course there wasn't a temple at the time
of יהושע, but maybe there was a משכן שילה, Mishkan Shiloh, maybe
that counted. דוד גזר בזמן שאין בית המקדש קיים, David gazar bi-zman
she-ein Beis HaMikdash kayam, דוד David made it for future generations or
when there is no temple. There was no temple at the time
of דוד, David and that's what דוד David added. Again, now what's
he adding? Is he adding servitude or is he adding not to
intermarry? So that's what I said before. תוספות Tosfos suggests that now
we're clearly talking about the issue of servitude, but the point is
if you're making, if you're making them slaves, the natural result of
making them slaves is that you can't intermarry. And now and so
then the. The question is is דוד now saying that דוד is
extending their idea of being slaves or is דוד making a גזירה
about just not intermarrying? Again, it's getting a little bit confused. Now
the גמרא Gemara ends by saying the following: top of י"ט עמוד
ב'. Yud Tes Amud Bais. בימי רבי, Bi'mei Rabbi, in the time
of רבי, ביקשו להתיר נתינים, bikshu le-hatir nesinim, they wanted to permit
the נתינים, presumably by not making them slaves, not to directly make
it permissible to marry, but at least to say they're no longer
slaves. And that they can do because like הפקר בית דין הפקר,
Hefker Beis Din Hefker, if it's a sense of being owned by
the people, then they can free that. אמר להם רבי, Amar lahem
Rabbi, רבי says, חלקינו ניטוש, chelkeinu natia, we can free our portion,
you know, release them from servitude to us, but חלק מזבח מי
יטוש, chelek mizbe'ach mi yatia, we can't—who is—we are not in a
position to release their sense of being servitude for purposes of the
temple? And therefore their status of slaves remains, and if their status
of slaves remains, then well, but they're when there will be a
temple they're owned by, you know, the temple whoever trust fund, exactly.
So and because they remain slaves, therefore they remain forbidden to intermarry.
ופליגא דרבי חייא בר אבא, U-pliga de-Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, this argues
with רבי חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, דרבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, de-Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, חלק
אדם לעולם אסור. chelek adam le-olam assur. The portion of the people
is forever forbidden, meaning unless they release it, but that portion remains.
חלק מזבח בזמן שבית המקדש קיים אסור, chelek mizbe'ach bi-zman she-Beis HaMikdash
kayam assur, when there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash they're owned by
the temple trust fund, אין בית המקדש קיים שרי, ein Beis HaMikdash
kayam shari, when there's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash they're no longer
owned by the temple trust fund. So therefore in theory the people
could release their portion and the נתינים could at least not be
slaves, maybe they could also be permitted to intermarry with if they
converted. Again, here the גמרא Gemara is being very unclear about whether
the focus here is on a sense of being slaves or is
the focus on the issue of intermarry. That's why I said תוספות
Tosfos sort of sees that maybe, you know, one results from the
other, that the intermarried prohibition comes from the slave. Or the simpler
way of certainly learning the earlier גמרא Gemara is that it was
just about marrying, it had nothing to do with being slaves.
Can they overturn it according to that?
Indirectly, if all what דוד did was make them slaves, then you
could sort of do הפקר בית דין הפקר. Hefker Beis Din Hefker.
Okay, moving on. That was the נתינים. Moving on. אמר רבי יהושע,
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, says רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, next משנה. Mishna. שמעתי
שסריס חולץ. Shamati she-saris choletz. Remember that חליצה? chalitzah? Okay, so we've
been doing so much about personal status and who you can marry
and not marry. One of the things we talked about recently was
of course פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה. Ptzua Daka u-Kshus Shafcha. Now we're
going to turn back into discussing issues of חליצה. chalitzah. Now I've
heard that a סריס saris can do חליצה. chalitzah. Now of course
our intuition would be that if you know somebody's a סריס, saris,
then he's not relevant for חליצה, chalitzah, and his wife isn't relevant
for יבום yibum because he's not in a category of being able
to להקים שם אחיו. le-hakim shem achiv. And if the guy who
died was a סריס, saris, he wasn't in the position of being
able to have kids, so you know to some degree that should
have taken this whole thing out of the פרשה. parsha. But רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, שמעתי שסריס חולץ, shamati she-saris choletz, I heard
that a סריס, saris, somebody who is literally a eunuch, somebody who
cannot have kids, does חליצה, chalitzah, וחולצין לאשתו, ve-choltzin le-ishto, or if
he died, you would do חליצה chalitzah with his wife. I'll see
what he came to with in a minute, we'll see in the
גמרא, Gemara we'll see, the גמרא's Gemara going to discuss, what's a
משנה Mishna you didn't discuss? And I also heard ושמעתי שסריס לא
חולץ ולא חולצין לאשתו, ve-saris lo choletz ve-lo choltzin le-ishto, that he
can't do חליצה chalitzah and you don't do חליצה chalitzah for his
wife. Namely the לפרש, le-fareish, I don't know how to reconcile these
two traditions. That's interesting, it's very interesting. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi
Akiva, says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, who is רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua
student, אני אפרש, ani afareish, I'll figure it out, I'll reconcile it.
סריס אדם חולץ וחולצין לאשתו. Saris adam choletz ve-choltzin le-ishto.
A person that has become סריס saris through human agency, which is
sort of like כרות שפכה, Kshus Shafcha, פצוע דכא, Ptzua Daka, through
some type of, you know, accident or intentional thing done, so that
person could do חליצה chalitzah and you could do חליצה chalitzah to
his wife. Why? מפני שהיתה לו שעת כושר, mipnei she-haysah lo sha'as
kosher, because at least when he began life he was able to
have kids. It was something that happened later, which means again, and
we've seen this idea before, even if it's quite funny, right? Here
a person can do חליצה, chalitzah, maybe even do יבום, yibum, we'll
see in the גמרא, Gemara, even though it would be impossible for
him right now to have to, you know, have this woman conceive,
you know, to impregnate this woman. But because as we would say
in בריסקר Brisker language, בגברא, be-gavra, you know, in terms of his
personal status he's not seen as completely out of the category of
having kids because when he was—until he was seven and had this
accident he could have—you know he had the equipment and ability to
have kids. So since at some stage in his life he had
that ability, then in terms of his personal status he's in the
פרשה. parsha. Even though for the last 20 years including up until
right now and for the rest of his life he'll never be
able to have kids, right? And therefore you would say it's absurd
to talk about him doing יבום, yibum, but since in terms of
his personal identity that's not something that's an intrinsic part of his
identity, he's able to do חליצה, chalitzah, maybe even able to do
יבום. yibum. And the same you would have to do חליצה chalitzah
or יבום yibum with his wife. That's one minute if
it's a סריס אדם. saris adam. So I thought it was supposed
to be—I understand. But that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. Now,
סריס חמה, saris chamah, if somebody was made a סריס saris by
the sun—now that's a funny language because what we're going to assume
it means in this context, you could have just said it meant
like I don't know somehow natural events as opposed to, you know,
some—but—but here we're saying specifically it means born with this problem. If
somebody was born with this problem, לא חולץ ולא חולצין לאשתו. lo
choletz ve-lo choltzin le-ishto. So he's out of the category, so you
wouldn't do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza with his wife, he wouldn't
be able to do יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitza, why? מפני שלא
הייתה לו שעת כושר. mipnei she-lo hayta lo sha'at kosher. Since he
was never in the category of being able to have kids, so
then as a personal status he's excluded, okay? And that's what רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva focuses on, not right now if it's possible, but
as a personal... in terms of your personal identity, is this intrinsic
to your identity or not? That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who was
רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua colleague, another teacher of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
says, לא כי, lo ki, that's not... that's not the distinction. It's
the opposite. אלא סריס חמה חולץ וחולצין לאשתו, ella sris chama choletz
ve-chotzin le-ishto,
somebody who has it natural can do חליצה chalitza and חליצה chalitza
can be done with his wife, why? מפני שיש לו רפואה, mipnei
she-yesh lo refua,
not just because he's not a פצוע דכא, ptzu'ah daka, but also
because somehow maybe if it was not something like, you know, if
it was just something a condition he was born with, maybe he'll
get better. סריס אדם לא חולץ ולא חולצין לאשתו מפני שאין לו
רפואה, sris adam lo choletz ve-lo chotzin le-ishto mipnei she-ein lo refua,
if it's something that happened through human agency, it cannot be healed.
Now I'm not exactly sure why the גמרא Gemara, assumes that difference,
it could be because סריס אדם sris adam it assumes means that
actually something anatomically has been done to him, like we learned before
about פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה, ptzu'ah daka u-khrut shofcha, you know, so
if there's actually been something severed or whatever, that's not going to
get better. But if somebody is just born infertile, you know, so
it's less obvious like what exactly the problem is, maybe that's something
that can actually correct itself, but somehow the גמרא Gemara understands that
that's the difference. So it also seems to be an issue of
right now, because we're accepting somebody right now impossible to have kids,
and nevertheless he could do חליצה, chalitza, you do חליצה chalitza with
his wife. So everybody agrees it's not about the issue about whether
right now it's possible or not. The question is how much is
it the identity of the person. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
it's the identity of the person if he was born with this
condition. It's not his identity if it came later. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says if his identity... it's a permanent condition. It's not seen
as part of his identity if it's something that potentially is reversible,
then it's not seen as part of his identity. Yes, Phil.
I think earlier on in the second section you established that the
only consequence of doing a חליצה chalitza that's not necessary is that
she'd be אסורה לכהן. asura le-kohen. Well, it seemed pretty lenient like
we didn't care so much about that. So why is it talked
about a lot of חליצות chalitzas that are like not necessary?
Well, that's when there's a... well, yes, but... so לא חולץ lo
choletz does mean that even if... as we're going to see, even
if you did a חליצה, chalitza, it does not affect her status.
A, it means it's not required, so if he's the only guy
around she walks free without a חליצה chalitza or יבום, yibum, and
B, it means that even if you do a חליצה, chalitza, it
doesn't affect her status, it'd be seen as meaningless.
קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, just do it.
No, I don't understand, because first of all, why do it? If
you don't require a חליצה, chalitza, everybody's better off. She doesn't have
to wait for the חליצה chalitza to be done, and her status
isn't affected for a כהן. kohen. When we said do a חליצה,
chalitza, that was a case where there was like some type of
a rabbinic problem or there was some type of a ספק. sofek.
So there was a need to want to do it, there was
something that needed to be addressed, and we said, well, address it
with a חליצה... chalitza... you can't address it with a יבום yibum
because of whatever issue, but address it with a חליצה. chalitza. Here,
if we're saying it's not necessary, everybody's better off. Okay, so now
the... let's finish the משנה. Mishna, It says, העיד יהושע בן בתירא,
heidid Yehoshua ben Betira, רבי יהושע בן בתירא Rabbi Yehoshua ben Betira
testified על בן מגוסת, al Ben Magusas,
a person by the name of בן מגוסת Ben Magusas שהיה בירושלים
she-haya bi-Yerushalayim סריס
אדם, sris adam, and he was in ירושלים Yerushalayim and he was
a סריס sris through human
agency, וייבמו את אשתו, ve-yibemu et ishto, and then he died and
they did יבום yibum with his wife, לקיים דברי רבי עקיבא, le-kayem
divrei Rabbi Akiva, and that... they didn't do it in order to
be מקיים דברי רבי עקיבא, mekayem divrei Rabbi Akiva, but that testimony
is a support to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Here was a case
of a סריס אדם sris adam that they actually went ahead and
did יבום yibum with his wife. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
that's the case where you still do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza
when a person was a סריס אדם, sris adam, when it was
a condition even a human that came later, not a condition he
was born with. And then it says,
now, הסריס לא חולץ ולא מייבם. ha-sris lo choletz ve-lo meyabem. It's
quite funny because we had this whole little whole discussion רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and then
you have like a סתם משנה stam Mishna afterwards which seems to
like just ignore all that earlier discussion and just says simply: a
סריס, sris, you don't do חליצה chalitza and you don't do יבום.
yibum. וכן אילונית לא חולצת ולא מתייבמת. ve-chen ailonit lo choletzet ve-lo
mityabemet. And an אילונית, ailonit, you don't do חליצה chalitza and יבום.
yibum. An אילונית ailonit is also a woman who can't give birth,
but similar, it's not just a woman who right now can't give
birth, right? The same way a סריס sris is a man that,
you know, some סריסים srisim yes, some סריסים srisim no, it's not
just the immediate inability, somehow it has to be something that's very
much about the person's identity that excludes them from the category. So
similarly by the case of an אילונית ailonit that is exempted from
יבום, yibum, it's not just a woman that's not having kids and
infertile, but something very much not an עקרה akara but an אילונית,
ailonit, and we'll see about the physical characteristics, but something that makes
her in terms of her own identity excluded from the category. לא
חולצת ולא מתייבמת, lo choletzet ve-lo mityabemet, so once you're out of
the category, then there's no obligation of חליצה chalitza and יבום, yibum,
and the same by the סריס sris whether he was the dead
husband or he is the surviving brother.
רבי אליעזר אומר יש לו רפואה, Rabbi Eliezer omer yesh lo refua,
right?
Well, the end of the משנה mishna doesn't know... doesn't seem to
know the first half of the משנה, mishna. it just says categorically.
Now,
הסריס שחלץ ליבמתו ha-sris she-chalatz le-yevamto לא פסלה. lo pasla. Now here
it's getting to Phil's issue, if the סריס seris goes ahead and
does חליצה chalitzah to his sister-in-law, it's not, it's like nothing was
done, she's not invalid to a כהן. kohen. It was a meaningless
act. ביאה, be'ah, if he had sex with her, פסלה, pasla, he
invalidated her, because since there's no מצות ייבום mitzvot yibbum with a
סריס, seris, so this act is an act of עריות, arayot, it's
אשת אח, eshet ach, brother's sister not in a place of the
מצוה mitzvah of ייבום, yibbum, because there's no מצוה mitzvah of ייבום
yibbum with him. So therefore, it was an איסור issur, of עריות,
arayot, and therefore she is now פסולה לכהונה, psulah le-khunah, she's a
חללה. chalalah. מפני שהיא בעילת זנות, mipnei she-hi be'ilat zenut, and not
just זנות, zenut, it's a בעילת עריות. be'ilat arayot. וכן אילונית, ve-khein
ailonit, similarly by an אילונית, ailonit, שחלצו לה אחים, she-chaltzu lah achim,
if one of the brothers does חליצה, chalitzah, לא פסלוה, lo pasluha,
they didn't invalidate her for a כהן, kohen, because there's no מצות
ייבום mitzvot yibbum with an אילונית ailonit and no מצות חליצה mitzvah
chalitzah with a meaningless act. בעלוה, be'aluha, if they had sex with
her, right, פסלוה, pasluha, then they invalidated her, because it wasn't a
מצות ייבום, mitzvah yibbum, it was an act of עריות, arayot, מפני
שבעילתה בעילת זנות. mipnei she-be'ilatah be'ilat zenut. So how do you deal
with the fact that the second part of the משנה mishna doesn't
know anything about the first part?
And it gets to this interesting question about to what degree, sometimes
you have earlier משניות mishnayot that are סתם stam and that the
later תנאים tannaim debate what the terms are of the earlier משנה.
mishna. You see this
often, gesundheit, like a משנה mishna beginning of
קידושין, kiddushin, right? האשה נקנית בכסף בשטר ובביאה. ha-ishah nikneit be-kesef be-shetar
u-be-ve'ah. כסף, kesef, how much כסף? kesef? בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
a דינר, dinar, בית הלל Beit Hillel says a פרוטה. perutah. Or
you know, you have a case like in the beginning of פסחים.
pesachim. It says any place you don't bring in חמץ chametz you
have to check. ולמה אמרו שתי שורות במרתף, ve-lama amru shtei shurot
ba-martef, what does it mean by that when you have to check
the two rows of the wine cellar? Well, בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says it means these rows, בית הלל Beit Hillel says it means
those rows. It seems clearly there was an early סתם teaching and
later תנאים tannaim debate what that early teaching means. So one could
imagine, right, it's very bizarre our משנה. mishna, You have this whole
discussion of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, and then it says סריס לא חולץ ולא חולצין לאשתו.
seris lo choletz ve-lo choltzin le-ishto. Well, with סריס, seris, you just
told me there were two types of סריס. seris. So it could
very well be that there was this early משנה mishna that said
הסריס לא חולץ ולא חולצין לאשתו, ha-seris lo choletz ve-lo choltzin le-ishto,
right? And then on that
משנה, mishna, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said I actually heard that sometimes
a סריס seris does חליצה chalitzah and then they have a whole
debate, right, which סריס seris does and does not, but it's all
sort of emerging from this סתם משנה stam mishna that we have
presented to us at the end. Logically it should have been at
the beginning, at the end, that just has it as a simple
statement. And then you have oh, that's very nice, the משנה mishna,
says no, but I actually heard some yes, and let's try to
figure out which is which.
Yeah, bit of clumsy editing.
Then it has it next. Yeah, it's a good point, right? It's
also funny that רבי doesn't want to tell us which way he's
פוסק, posek, פוסק. paskening. You've got all these opinions and then you
say afterwards just simply, if anything you would say by the juxtaposition
maybe it's trying to teach us that a סריס seris never either
category because you gave different opinions and then you didn't distinguish. But
yes, it is funny. Anyway.
Yes.
And so can
he marry an אילונית?
ailonit? Yep, she's not a גרושה, gerushah,
she's not going to have children, right?
But yeah, כהן kohen doesn't have to be able to marry, even
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol only has to marry a בתולה, betulah,
he doesn't have to marry a fertile one. Okay. All right. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. מכדי, mikhdei, let's take a
look. Now the גמרא Gemara has a fascinating question, even though we
dealt with this משנה, mishna, this bizarre idea that you could do
חליצה chalitzah and ייבום yibbum with someone that can't have kids as
long as they're not like בגברא be-gavra categorically excluded. The גמרא Gemara
has a different issue. מכדי, mikhdei, says the גמרא, Gmara let's take
a look. שמענא ליה לרבי עקיבא דאמר חייבי לאוין כחייבי כריתות דמי.
shmana leh le-Rabbi Akiva de-amar chayvei lavin ke-chayvei keritot dami. We know
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that somebody who's forbidden by a לאו
lav is like somebody who is an איסור כרת, issur karet, which
means that the kids are ממזר mamzer, and that there's no קידושין.
kiddushin. And which also
means, remember the principle by ייבום yibbum going back to the first
משנה, that if the woman is forbidden to the brother because of
an איסור כרת, issur karet, then it's like excluded from the מצוה
mitzvah of ייבום, yibbum, right? So here's the problem. According to רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, which type of a סריס seris does חליצה? chalitzah?
Somebody who's a סריס אדם. seris adam. A סריס אדם seris adam
is what? Presumably a פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה, ptzu'a daka ve-khroot shofcha,
who is forbidden with an איסור לאו issur lav to marry a
Jewish woman. So how can there be a מצוה mitzvah of חליצה
chalitzah and ייבום? yibbum? It should be like an איסור כרת issur
karet for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because he says the kid of
such a union is a ממזר, mamzer there's no קידושין, kiddushin, all
these types of things. So it should be just completely excluded from
the category of ייבום. yibbum. מכדי שמענא ליה לרבי עקיבא דאמר חייבי
לאוין כחייבי כריתות דמי, וחייבי כריתות לאו בני חליצה וייבום נינהו. mikhdei
shmana leh le-Rabbi Akiva de-amar chayvei lavin ke-chayvei keritot dami, ve-chayvei keritot
lav benei chalitzah ve-yibbum ninhu. We know that if there's an איסור
כרת issur karet like an ערווה, ervah, going back to the very
first משנה, there's no חליצה chalitzah and ייבום. yibbum. So how could
he say there's חליצה chalitzah and ייבום yibbum by a case of
a brother who's a פצוע דכא? ptzu'a daka? So
who's a סריס אדם? seris adam? So אמר רבי אמי הכא במאי
עסקינן כגון שנשא אחיו גיורת. amar Rabbi Ammi hakha be-mai askinan kegon
she-nasa achiv giyoret.
Ah, his sister-in-law is a convert, right? And there's no איסור, issur.
as we learned before, of סריס, seris, of פצוע דכא ptzu'a daka
with a convert. Okay. And that's why it's possible to do it,
there's no איסור. issur. ורבי עקיבא סבר לה כרבי יוסי דאמר קהל
גרים לא איקרי קהל. ve-Rabbi Akiva savar lah ke-Rabbi Yossi de-amar kehal
gerim lo ikri kehal. He held like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who
says a קהל
גרים kehal gerim is not considered the קהל, kehal, so there's no
prohibition of a פצוע דכא ptzu'a daka to marry a גיורת. giyoret.
And that's why, that's the scenario we're talking about, that there's no
איסור. issur אי הכי, i hakhi, says the גמרא, Gmara if so...
That's true, יבומי נמי מיבם. yebumei nami meyaben. Why, why is it
talking about you can do חליצה? chalitza? He should say you too
do, you can do יבום. yibum. If we were talking about that
they weren't גירים, geirim, we understand why he doesn't talk about doing
יבום yibum because it's אסור assur because it's פצוע דכא, ptzua daka,
right? But if in order you can't have it be an איסור
לאו issur lav for Rabbi Akiva because then it would exclude him.
So we have to be talking about a גיורת. giyoret. So then
why are we not talking about יבום? yibum? So אי הכי נמי,
in hachi nami, you're right. You could do יבום. yibum. ואיידי דאמר
רבי יהושע חולץ, ve'aydi d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua choletz, since Rabbi Yehoshua says
I heard that sometimes you're חולץ choletz and Rabbi Yehoshua would have
to say חולץ choletz because according to Rabbi Yehoshua maybe a פצוע
דכא ptzua daka can't marry a גר. ger. So because maybe you
know he holds that קהל גירים kahal geirim is איקרי קהל. ikrei
kahal. So Rabbi Yehoshua had to say חולץ choletz because Rabbi Yehoshua
didn't want you know once it's a פצוע דכא ptzua daka Rabbi
Yehoshua didn't want to marry anybody, even a גר. ger. But Rabbi
Akiva wouldn't have a problem with that. אמר איהו נמי חולץ amar
ihu nami choletz he said חולץ choletz but really in principle you
could do יבום. yibum. So we have to get it out of
being the איסור issur of פצוע דכא, ptzua daka, we say we're
talking about a גיורת. giyoret. And since we're talking about a גיורת
giyoret therefore in principle you could even do and a גיורת giyoret
according to Rabbi Akiva would not be a problem of a פצוע
דכא ptzua daka and a גיורת. giyoret. So once there's no לאו
lav we could even be talking according to him even about doing
יבום. yibum. דיקא נמי deika nami that also can be
inferred דתניא העיד רבי יהושע בן בתירה על בן מנוסס מגוסת
שהיה בירושלים סריס אדם ביבמו את אשתו לקיים דברי רבי עקיבא. detanya
he'id Rabbi Yehoshua ben Beteira al ben Menusas megusas shehaya biyerushalayim sris
adam biyibmu et ishto lekayem divrei Rabbi Akiva. The phrase that supports
Rabbi Akiva is when the wife of a סריס sris and they
did a יבום. yibum. שמע מינה shma mina we see we're talking
not just about the possibility of חליצה, chalitza, we see we're talking
even about the possibility of יבום. yibum. Of course that's when the
dead guy was a סריס, sris, but the גמרא assumes it is
the same. Okay, so therefore how do you deal with the fact
that according to Rabbi Akiva if he's a סריס אדם sris adam
there's an איסור לאו issur lav and that should exclude you from
the category of יבום yibum and חליצה? chalitza? We say we're talking
about a גיורת. giyoret. There's no איסור issur with a גיורת giyoret
according to Rabbi Akiva and in that case either חליצה chalitza and
even יבום yibum is a possibility.
Okay. מתיב רבא. mative Rava. Rava asks on this. Okay,
פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה, ptzua daka vechrut shofcha, so those are סריסי
אדם. srisei adam. סריס אדם sris adam which somehow maybe is something
that isn't a פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה ptzua daka vechrut shofcha but
okay all similar categories. והזקן ve'hazaken and even an elderly person who
now is no longer able to have kids. או חולצין או מיבמין.
o chaltzin o meyabmin. You can do חליצה chalitza or יבום. yibum.
That's fine. That works with Rabbi Akiva. Okay, it's somebody who was
not born with the condition, got the condition later, either because something
you know physically anatomically happened or he just got old. And this
person is able to do חליצה chalitza and יבום. yibum. That's consistent
with Rabbi Akiva that says when it happens later you're okay. כיצד,
keitzad, מתו metu if these people died, the people with these conditions,
this סריס אדם, sris adam, ולהם נשים velahem nashim and they had
left and you know they left a wife behind. ולהם אחים velahem
achim and they have brothers. So there's still a מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum and חליצה chalitza now. ועמדו אחים ve'amdu achim and the
brothers got up ועשו מאמר בנשותיהם ve'asu maamar binshoteihem even if they
did מאמר maamar או שנתנו גט o shenatnu get or they gave
גט get או שחלצו o shechaltzu or they did חליצה. chalitza. מה
שעשו עשוי. ma she'asu asui. It's all good, it all is binding.
It's like a normal case. ואם בעלו ve'im ba'alu and if instead
they did ביאה, biah, had did יבום, yibum, had sex, קנו, kanu,
it works. It's funny that it has to spell it all out
but you shouldn't be any confusion. Even though the dead husbands were
סריס אדם, sris adam, totally normal in all הלכות halachot of יבום
yibum and חליצה.
chalitza. That assumes that all the brothers are normal, right?
Well, no, now we're going to do the flip case. מתו אחים,
metu achim, now let's say the brothers died, meaning the brothers who
didn't have this condition died and now they, the ones that have
this condition, are the ones that are obligated in יבום yibum and
חליצה. chalitza. ועמדו הם ועשו מאמר בנשותיהם. ve'amdu hem ve'asu maamar binshoteihem.
So whatever they did will also work. Whether it was מאמר maamar
ונתנו גט venatnu get or a גט get או חלצו, o chaltzu,
מה שעשו עשוי. ma she'asu asui. It's good. ואם בעלו קנו. ve'im
ba'alu kanu. And if they had sex it works. So it doesn't
matter whether they're the dead husbands or they're the living brothers or
maybe even both, right? It works. If you have this condition, it
does not change the status for the הלכות halachot of יבום yibum
and חליצה. chalitza.
ואם לא בשמך יקרא בשם אחיו בישראל. ve'im lo bishmecha yikarei beshem
achiv beyisrael. And the גמרא is going to get to that.
Right, the גמרא is going to get to that. That's the obvious
problem throughout this thing. It's all very nice to say categorically in
the category, not in the category, at the end of the day
you're not having kids. The גמרא will get to that. We're not
up to that yet. ואסור לקיימן. ve'assur lekayman. And even though all
these things work and it's a normal מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum
and חליצה, chalitza, they're not allowed to stay married to their wife
to these women if they go ahead and do יבום. yibum. Why?
שנאמר לא יבא פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה בקהל ה' lo yavo ptzua
daka vechrut shofcha bikhal Hashem because it's a, you're transgressing that prohibition.
It might be יבום yibum and חליצה chalitza applies, but you're not
allowed to stay married. So what do you see? You see we're
talking that they're not גירים. geirim. They're not the women aren't
גיורות, giyorot, right? Because there still is the prohibition. But this is
following the Rabbi Akiva idea that if it's a סריס אדם sris
adam it's יבום yibum and חליצה chalitza works. But now we're back
to our problem. You're dealing with a סריס אדם, sris adam, you're
dealing with the prohibition of
לא יבא פצוע דכא lo yavo ptzua daka and you're still why
isn't this whole thing excluded because it's like a חייבי כריתות, chayvei
kritot, right? So that should just once it's an איסור לאו issur
lav it should completely exclude everything from the category. So the גמרא
says אלמא בקהלות קיימינן. alma b’khalos k’inan.
You see we're talking about a case where the prohibition applies by
the קהל, kahal, not by גרים, geirim, or to say the prohibition
applies to גרים geirim anyway. So what do you see? So you
see we're dealing with in רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position and somehow
we're ignoring the fact that the איסור לאו issur lav should exclude
it completely. So אלא אמר רבא ela amar Rava כגון שנפלו לו
בסוף
נפצעו. kegon shenaflo lo besof nif tzu. Oh what happened was is
the condition occurred after the guy died and therefore it doesn't change
the and therefore even though it's like a חייבי כריתות, chayavei krisus,
if it that would if it at the moment that the מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibum applied it was you were obligated even if
the איסור issur comes later that doesn't change the status for יבום.
yibum.
I mean meaning
the guy died, everybody was healthy, okay,
and then the right then the surviving brother, right, of course it
could have said that we're dealing with cases even the dead guy
did, but okay, then the surviving brother became a סריס, saris, so
that wouldn't change the status vis-a-vis יבום. yibum. There'd still be a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. So now the גמרא says אמר ליה
אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said is that really true? ודחי
איסור פצוע ונדחי איסור עשה דיבום. vedachi issur ptzua venidchei issur asei
d'yibum.
So what? The new status of פצוע ptzua should override the מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibum even if it came later. מי לא תנן
mi lo tnan we taught רבן גמליאל אומר Rabban Gamliel omer אם
מיאנה מיאנה. im miana miana. So this is a case where a
man was married to an underage girl right? It was only a
rabbinic marriage, the mother and the brothers did it and then this
girl's sister fell in front of him for a מצוה mitzvah of
יבום. yibum. So right you remember those scenarios. So now you got
a case of אחות אשה achos isha but this woman that he's
married to isn't yet technically his wife. So one thing you say
to this underage girl is do מיאון miun so that your your
husband now can do the real מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah d'oraisa of יבום
yibum with your sister. So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says if she
does מיאון miun good. ואם לאו v'im lav if she refuses to
do מיאון miun תמתין עד שתגדיל tamtin ad shetagdil wait till she
becomes an adult and then the woman he's married to the underage
girl will then legally become his wife ותצא הלזו vsetzei halazu and
then her sister who you know who was the brother's wife will
leave משום אחות אשה. mishum achos isha. So meaning what's the scenario?
When the brother died he had a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum
with this woman that he was married to her underage sister. But
when if you wait a while and that underage girl becomes a
woman and becomes his legal wife the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum
goes away because now it becomes his wife's sister right because he
just waited till his underage wife grew up. So you see that
when the status changes afterwards it still uproots the מצוה mitzvah of
יבום. yibum. This woman became his wife's sister and the מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibum stopped even though at the moment of death. So
here too even if you become a סריס saris it should undermine
the מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. So אלמא alma you see אתי
איסור אחות אשה ודחי. ati issur achos isha vedachi. When the status
of wife's sister comes along it pushes off. הכא נמי תיתי איסור
פצוע ונדחי hacha nami tesei issur ptzua venidchei here even if it
comes later it should push it off. So we're stuck again. How
according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva do you have a מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibum together with the איסור of פצוע דכא? ptzua daka?
The איסור פצוע דכא issur ptzua daka should uproot the מצוה mitzvah
of יבום. yibum. So let's just read the answer. The answer
is
אלא אמר רב יוסף האי תנא האי תנא דבי רבי עקיבא היא
דאמר מחייבי לאוין דשאר הוי ממזר מחייבי לאוין גרידי לא הוי ממזר.
ela amar Rav Yosef hai tanna hai tanna d'vei Rabbi Akiva hi
d’amar mechayavei lavin d’she’er havei mamzer mechayavei lavin geridei lo havei mamzer.
Okay which is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva there's two opinions in רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. When רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says an איסור לאו
issur lav is like an איסור כרת issur kareis and the child
is a ממזר mamzer does he say it by every איסור לאו
issur lav even let's say מחזיר גרושתו machazir grushaso even you know
פצוע דכא ptzua daka or does he only say it by an
איסור לאו issur lav that is about a relationship a חייבי לאוין
דשאר chayavei lavin d’she’er I mean about a what do you call
it about a type of an incest relationship? About like yeah well
right meaning that has to do with being related, not relationship where
it has to do. So you know which would be what would
be an איסור לאו issur lav of of a שאר? she'er? I'd
have to go back and check. Anyway but I think there's רש"י
Rashi say here? Hold on. What's
רש"י? Rashi? No means not every איסור לאו. issur lav. It
is
one minute.
I'm sorry I forgot exactly what the case hold on what's the
חייבי לאוין
דשאר. chayavei
lavin d’she’er.
Oh אנוסת אביו anusas aviv would be an example.
Okay so so you know what I'll we'll revisit this tomorrow but
the basic point is that there are some איסורי לאו issurei lav
like this case which is פצוע דכא ptzua daka that has nothing
to do with being somewhat related to the person. It's just a
simple לאו lav that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would not say is
like an איסור כרת issur kareis and the child is not a
ממזר and therefore is not excluded from the מצוה mitzvah of יבום.
yibum. The types of איסור לאו issur lav that רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says are treated like real עריות arayos that are The types
of איסור לאו *issur lav* that Rabbi Akiva says are treated like
real עריות *arayos* that are excluded completely from the מצוה *mitzvah* of
יבום *yibum* and the child would be a ממזר *mamzer* are ones
that have to do with a degree of relatedness to because you're
related to them in some way. Things that are on איסור לאו
*issur lav*. פצוע דכא *ptzuah daka* isn't in this category. It's a
simple לאו *lav* of a person you're not related to and therefore
the child is not a ממזר *mamzer*. I don't know if you
could be having children with a פצוע דכא *ptzuah daka* but anyway
okay. What?
אשת איש *eishes ish* doesn't mean related like biologically?
No, אשת איש *eishes ish* is, yeah, אשת איש *eishes ish* is
anyway, you know what, we'll revisit it tomorrow. אשת איש *eishes ish*
is anyway
excluded because of what he called, because because of the other thing
we learned before. So אשת איש *eishes ish* is not one of
the cases where Rabbi Akiva would say it's like an ערוה *ervah*
because אשת איש *eishes ish* isn't because you're related to them, it's
because of the marriage. But it's an איסור כרת *issur kares* anyway,
so it doesn't matter. It doesn't need to be excluded. It's already
in the group of things that are excluded because they're an איסור
כרת *issur kares*.